<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The doctrine of free-grace, no doctrine of licenciousnesse, or, That Gods free unconditionall pardoning of sinne is the best way to mortifie the power of sinne in believers asserted and cleared by Edward Bagshawe ...</title>
            <author>Bagshaw, Edward, 1629-1671.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 97 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29090</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B410</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5497</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12190844</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12190844</idno>
            <idno type="VID">55864</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29090)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 55864)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 119:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The doctrine of free-grace, no doctrine of licenciousnesse, or, That Gods free unconditionall pardoning of sinne is the best way to mortifie the power of sinne in believers asserted and cleared by Edward Bagshawe ...</title>
                  <author>Bagshaw, Edward, 1629-1671.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 39 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Abraham Miller for the author ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Grace (Theology)</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:55864:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:55864:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE DOCTRINE OF FREE-GRACE, NO DOCTRINE OF LICENCIOUSNESSE. OR, That Gods Free Unconditionall pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Sinne, is the beſt way to Mortifie the Power of Sinne in Believers. Aſſerted and Cleared, By <hi>Edward Bagſhawe</hi> Student of <hi>Ch. Ch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Abraham Miller</hi> for the Author, and are to be ſold by the Bookſellers in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1662.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:55864:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:55864:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mong thoſe many Falſe and Dangerous Opinions, which in this Age are let looſe upon us; there is none that is either more De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive of the True Nature of Chriſtian Religion, or more likely to be imbraced by ſome ſeemingly zealous and devout men, than the Doctrine of <hi>Free-will:</hi> whereby the <hi>Grace of God</hi> is rendred either altogether Needleſſe, or at beſt only a Coadjutor and partial Aſſiſtant to Mens Salvation.</p>
            <p>Were not men Naturally willing to follow that which ſerves to puff them up, and begets an opinion in them, that they are <hi>like Gods:</hi> I ſhould wonder how the Opinion of <hi>Free-will</hi> could ever finde any Learned Aſſertour; ſince the Reaſons againſt it, ever upon a Philoſophical account, are ſuch as no Wit of man is able to anſwer. For the ſubordination of Cauſes, and the Neceſſity that every Effect, ſhould have a Cauſe, which did produce it, is ſo ſtrong an Argument, that the Will of man is ſubject to the enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing influence of the Cauſes which move and determine it; that the moſt Learned of the Heathen, did upon this ſcore altogether re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject <hi>Free-will;</hi> and yet this ſuppoſed. Fatality in every Action, did not at all leſſen or abate their ſtrict adherence to, and proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Virtue: None having been more famous in this kinde than the <hi>Stoicks,</hi> which were the Known Aſſertors and Maintainers of <hi>Neceſſity.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:55864:3"/>
            <p>But without entring into any ſuch kind of Diſpute, the Apoſtle having already forbidden us to medale <hi>with things which we have not ſeen,</hi> and it being according to him plain folly <hi>to affirm too poſitively about things we know not:</hi> I ſhall not ſcruple to admit that, as to things of meerly Civil Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ment, God hath endued the will of every man, with a Liberty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> juſtify himſelf; and that we are not ſo tied up by the Concurrence of Cauſes, but that a man hath power over his own Will, to embrace or to refuſe any thing tendred to him, with or without Reaſon, as he himſelf pleaſes. While I ſay I am content to admit this, my meaning is not that I underſtand how this can be done (for I muſt profeſſe it is to me altogether unintelligible) yet becauſe it contradicts no <hi>Article of Faith,</hi> and likewiſe ſerves beſt to demonſtrate the Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Humane Laws, which are all founded upon that ſuppoſition; I think it altogether a Needleſſe thing to diſpute about <hi>Free-will</hi> in Moral Actions, and a very Abſurd thing to deny it. Since in matters which are capable of Contrary Reaſonings, to follow the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncontradicted and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Aſſent of Mankind, is much more Safe and Prudent, than to tread in New paths; there being but little difference, as to the Effect, between an Apparant Error, and a Suspected, becauſe <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nneceſſary Truth.</p>
            <p>But how deſirous ſoever I am to comply with the Common Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lepſis and Inbred Notion of <hi>Free-will,</hi> as to Humane Actions; yet as to the things of God, I muſt altogether deny it. For it is ſo clear, <hi>That the Things of God, none can underſtand,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently not Practice, <hi>but the Spirit of God,</hi> and thoſe, to whom that Spirit makes them both Plain and Eaſie; that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle urgeth that Sentence, not as a Truth then newly diſcovered to him, but as a Principle founded in Nature, and apparent by its own Equity and Reaſonablineſſe: And what the Scripture every where mentions concerning the Actings of the Spirit upon Believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, the Experience of all Believers that ever were in the World, is able to evidence; ſince ſuch muſt needs confeſſe, that there can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be a more dangerous Enemy to the <hi>Truths of God,</hi> then the <hi>Underſtanding;</hi> nor more Rebellious to the <hi>Precepts of God,</hi> than the <hi>Will</hi> of <hi>Man;</hi> untill the Spirit of God hath enlightned the one, and by his own Immediate Worke, mightily overpowred the other.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:55864:3"/>
            <p>For the proof of this, I might content my ſelf with what I find conteined in the bare letter of Scripture, to which, if we are what we profeſſe, we ought to captivate our own Reaſonings; but ſince many men, and thoſe not of leaſt Note even in our own Church, plead for that Idol <hi>Free-will,</hi> from the many Abſurdities which would follow, ſhould it not be granted; I ſhall undertake to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate, that much more pernicious Conſequences will follow, ſhould it once be admitted. For</p>
            <p>Firſt, It totally deſtroyes all belief of Gods Power and Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, in his ordering and guidance of Actions according to his own Will: For who is there, that underſtands any thing of Gods Sovereignty, but muſt needs acknowledge, that he foreſaw and predetermined every thing long before it was actually in being; but were there ſuch an Independent and Abſolute <hi>Free-will</hi> in Man, as ſome contend for, how the motions of his Will could be fore-ſeen is altogether Inconceivable: <hi>Socinus</hi> therefore, who ſaw how much this Argument did preſſe him, did make no ſcruple to deny Gods <hi>Preſcience:</hi> thereby doing that very thing, which <hi>Auſtine</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of in <hi>Tully, Dum fecit liberos, fecit etiam Sacrilegos: While he made Men Free, he did moſt ſacrilegiouſly rob God of his chief Prerogative,</hi> and that is, his <hi>Omniſcience:</hi> The <hi>Arminians</hi> therefore, who grant both <hi>Preſcience</hi> in God, and <hi>Free-will</hi> in Man, do admit both parts of the Contradiction to be True; and ſo not onely thwart the expreſſe Revelation of Scripture, which every where inculcates Gods <hi>Abſolute</hi> and <hi>Irreſpective Election,</hi> but likewiſe ſpeak that, which, in Reaſon (to which they pretend ſo much) neither themſelves nor any one elſe can poſſibly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Opinion of <hi>Free-will</hi> utterly cuts off all manner of Prayer: For whereas the greateſt Argument of Prayer ought either to be for <hi>Pardoning</hi> or <hi>Preventing Grace;</hi> with what face can he aske for <hi>Pardon,</hi> who by owning himſelf to have a ſufficient Power to do Gods Will, doth thereby acknowledge all his ſins, not to proceed from Surprize, Inadvertency or Weakneſſe; but to be ſins of his Will, and therein himſelf to be a Wilfull and a Malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Tranſgreſſour? The Saints of old did uſe to plead for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, their <hi>Raſhneſs</hi> and <hi>Haſte,</hi> as <hi>David;</hi> their <hi>Ignorance</hi> and <hi>Unbelief,</hi> as <hi>Paul;</hi> their <hi>Incogitancy</hi> and <hi>Unmindfulneſs,</hi> as <hi>John;</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:55864:4"/> but he that holds <hi>Free-will;</hi> makes all thoſe Apologies to be vain and uſeleſſe, ſince every offence in ſuch an one muſt needs ariſe from his own Reſolved and Deſigned Pravity; and ſins of Infirmity in others, in him are ſins of ſtrength; becauſe he might have avoided them, and would not. which diſcovers ſo groſſe an Enmity and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition againſt God, that all the while, that ſentence remains upon Record, <hi>If we ſinne wilfully after we have received the knowledg of the Truth, there remains no more Sacrifice for ſinne;</hi> it will be impoſſible for ſuch an one to look up with Faith, and believingly to ſue out his Pardon. And as with Pardoning, ſo likewiſe will it ſit with Preventing and ſtrengthning Grace; Free-will makes the one Deſperate, and the other <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſeleſſe. For what need I pray for that, which I have already by me; nay, which I am ſure ſhall never, ſo long as I am a man, be taken from me. No man prayes for the Money that is in his Cheſt; nor for thoſe goods, that he ſtands poſſeſſed of: So neither can we, without being guilty of <hi>Vain-babling,</hi> pray for ſtrength to do Gods will, if we think every man Naturally hath a power to do it, <hi>I will pray</hi> (ſaid one of the moſt learned Aſſertors of <hi>Free-will,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tully.</note> 
               <hi>for Fortune and Riches, for theſe are in Gods Gift; but not for Virtue, for that I can give my ſelf.</hi> Whereas he that knows he ſtands by Grace; that he cannot doe any thing well, but as the Spirit of God doth act him: and that the Actings of the Spirit, are Arbitrary, not at ours, but at his own Diſpoſal; he will find a Neceſſity upon him, to be often begging for that ſtrength, which he ſees he wants, and God alone can furniſh him with.</p>
            <p>Thirdly; Another Inconvenience of this Opinion of <hi>Free-will</hi> is, that it muſt needs betray poor Sinners to a delaying and putting off their Repentance: For he that finds it written, how ready God is to pardon upon Repentance; and is told withall, that it lies in his power to Repent, whenever he pleaſes; cannot be wrought upon by any Argument that I know of, to forbear his ſinfull pleaſures for the Moment. At leaſt, why he ſhould make ſuch haſte, as the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture doth preſſe us to, there can be no Imaginable Motive. For if I live according to this Doctrine, I ſhall be ſure to give my ſelf <hi>Repentance;</hi> becauſe I have a Natural Ability to do it; and that any man now living ſhould be ſo ſuddenly ſtrook, as not to have time enough for that Work, (which whenever it is done, it is done in a
<pb facs="tcp:55864:4"/> moment, though it may perhaps not be evidenced ſo ſoon) is ſo much ods, that any Sinner may ſafely venture to try a little longer the pleaſures of Sinne, before he reſolves by too ſudden a Repentance to leave them. Whereas he that owns every good Motion inviting that way, to be, not the Impulſe of his own Heart, but the Calling of Gods Spirit; which, like light, may ſhine for a time, and ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly be withdrawn again; he will find himſelf engaged to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer at the firſt Call; leaſt, while he tarries, God leaves off to call him, and gives him over as unworthy of Mercy, becauſe of his Stubborn Refuſall.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> It is impoſſible but thoſe who are leavened with this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, muſt needs be ſwelled with Pride; and puffed up with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of themſelves, above all other men: ſince they imagin all their Graces, to be purely the reſult of their own well managing and improving their Naturall Abilities. This was the Temper of the Phariſees heretofore, <hi>who juſtified themſelves and deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed others;</hi> for as <hi>Joſephus</hi> tells us, they were extremely addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to the Opinion of <hi>Free-will;</hi> and it appears in that they ſo much overvalued their own Power, that they would needs be more <hi>Holy</hi> and <hi>Righteous</hi> than the Law of God commanded; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore found out. <hi>New Ceremonies,</hi> and many ſelf-invented Forms of Devotion, which were their <hi>Works of Supererogation:</hi> which Humour ſtill reignes, as a Naturall Effect of it, among all thoſe ſeverall Parties, where the Opinion of <hi>Free-will</hi> is entertained. Whereas the Acknowledging that <hi>Gods Grace</hi> onely fills the Soul, and we, like Empty Veſſels, have nothing but what we daily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, will keep the Mind humble and Thankfull as to God; and likewiſe Tender and Compaſſionate towards others, who may for the preſent want the ſame Mercy which we enjoy.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, I might adde, that the whole Practice of <hi>Will-worſhip,</hi> whether it relates to the Inventing of uncommanded Methods in Divine Worſhip, or to the Impoſing of ſuch uſages upon others, is altogether founded upon a ſuppoſition that every Man hath <hi>Free-will;</hi> and therefore Magiſtrates conceiving it doth not ariſe from Tenderneſs of Conſcience, but meerly from an Affected Obſtinacy, that Men ſubmit not to their Injunctions, it makes them more Harſh and Rigorous in exacting Obedience, than otherwiſe they would ever attempt to doe; which thing alone makes the Belief of
<pb facs="tcp:55864:5"/> 
               <hi>Free-will in Religious matters,</hi> altogether inconſiſtent with and deſtructive of the Peace of Chriſtian ſocieties; as every age, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in there hath been the leaſt dawings of Spirituall Light doth abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly evidence. All the ſufferings of the Saints, having been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted upon them upon this ſingle account, in that when they refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to <hi>Worſhip the Beaſt or his Image,</hi> their Perſecutors thought, it lay in their Power, to doe him that Homage; whereas indeed it did not, it being impoſſible for any to avoid or forbear acting ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Dictates of a Well-grounded and Conſcientious Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion.</p>
            <p>But when as in oppoſition to all this, the maintainers of <hi>Free-will,</hi> doe urge that the Contrary Doctrine of Free Grace doth <hi>open a door to all manner of Licentiouſneſs, ſince by leaving no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in mans power, it leaves them free to doe nothing;</hi> and likewiſe, that <hi>it makes void and Ineffectuall all Gods Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, which ſuppoſe a Power of Obeying in us, or elſe they had been given in vain:</hi> which Objections being managed by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of much Rhetorick, and outward Sanctity, doe make a great Impreſſion upon a Slight and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nwary Reader: I have therefore in this Treatiſe, fully, at leaſt to my own ſatisfaction, anſwered both thoſe Objections; and have as I hope ſufficiently demonſtrated, that nothing doth more incline the ſoul to a Cheerfull Obedience, than a right <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding of the Doctrine of <hi>Free-grace;</hi> which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is the buſineſs of this Book to evidence, I will no longer detain the Reader from it, but recommend It, for its Succeſs and Iſſue, to the ſame Grace, which firſt gave it Birth and Beginning.</p>
            <closer>
               <date>
                  <hi>June 11 1662.</hi>
               </date>
               <signed>Edward Bagſhawe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Page 4. line 24. dele <hi>but.</hi> p. 19. l. 28. read <hi>but by the.</hi> p. 30. l. 23, 24. dele () p. 35. l. 4. r. <hi>Affections.</hi> ib. l. 17. r. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:55864:5"/>
            <head>THE Doctrine of <hi>FREE-GRACE</hi> no Doctrine of Licentiouſneſs.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Rom. 6.1, 2.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>What ſhall we ſay then? ſhall we continue in ſinne that Grace may abound? Farre be it: How ſhall we that are dead to ſinne, live any longer therein?</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe are the words of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> brought in by way of Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, againſt; and of Anſwer, for, that Doctrine of <hi>Free-Grace,</hi> which he doth in this Epiſtle ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly handle: For the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his Diſcourſe, we muſt have recourſe unto <hi>Chap.</hi> 3. where after a long and accurate handling of this Queſtion,<note place="margin">verſ. 28.</note> 
               <hi>How a man comes to be Juſtified in the ſight of God?</hi> the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle concludes <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>We inferre therefore,</hi> or, <hi>Argue from the Premiſes</hi> (as the word ſignifies) <hi>that a Man, is juſtified by Faith, without the Works of the Law.</hi> The reaſon and ground or which Aſſertion is this,<note place="margin">verſ. 20.</note> 
               <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by the Law is the knowledge of ſinne,</hi> i. e. A ſtrict and impartiall view of the Law, in its latitude and ſpirituall
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:55864:6"/> ſignificancy; and comparing of our Lives with it, is ſo farre from diſcovering the Rectitude of our Nature and Actions, that it rather ſerves to manifeſt the Obliquity and ſinfullneſs of them both: And therefore there muſt be ſome other expedient found out to <hi>Acquit</hi> or <hi>Juſtifie</hi> men in the ſight of God,<note place="margin">verſ. 27.</note> than an appeal unto the <hi>Law of Works;</hi> and that is, <hi>the Law of Faith,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, <hi>The Righteouſneſs of God, (i. e.</hi> which avails be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God,<note place="margin">verſ. 22.</note> and is accepted by him) <hi>is by Faith of Jeſus Christ, unto all, and upon all them that believe; for there is no difference. For all have ſinned, and come ſhort of the Glory of God,</hi> (whereby is meant, either the Graces which God requires, or the Happineſs which he promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: Men were not of themſelves able to perform the one, and therefore had no Right or Title unto the other) whereupon it follows, that all ſuch as are Juſtified, <hi>are Juſtified Freely by his Grace, through the Redemption, that is in,</hi> or by <hi>Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Doctrine, which doth ſo levell the Pride of man, by putting his Salvation quite out of himſelf and therein is utterly contradictory to humane conception, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle foreſaw, would meet with great oppoſition, and therefore that he might Aſſert and Clear this Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Truth from all poſſibility of Cavill, he urges and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers three of the main Objections, which either are or can be alleaged againſt it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>1</label> The firſt Objection is taken from the Example of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> concerning whom the common opinion of the Jews was, that he was <hi>Juſtified by Works;</hi> which they gathered from Gods renewing his <hi>Bleſsing</hi> upon him, after his ſignall obedience in attempting to offer his ſonne. <hi>For now I know,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 22.12.</note> ſaith God, <hi>that thou feareſt God, ſeeing thou haſt not withheld thy ſonne, thine onely ſonne from me.</hi> And
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:55864:6"/> again, <hi>Becauſe thou haſt done this thing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">verſ. 16, 17.</note> 
               <hi>and haſt not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held thy ſonne, thine onely ſonne; In bleſsing I will bleſs thee.</hi> Whereupon the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> ſeems clearly to Affirm, that <hi>Abraham</hi> was juſtified by his Works, in that Queſtion, <hi>Was not Abraham our Father Justified by Works, when he had offered Iſaac his ſonne upon the Altar?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this Inſtance,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſw.</note> the Apoſtle anſwers by directly deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that <hi>Abraham was Juſtified by Works;</hi> for proof of which, he quotes a place out of the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 13.6.</note> That <hi>Abraham believed in God, and it,</hi> i. e. that Faith of his, <hi>was imputed to him for Righteouſneſs.</hi> Which was ſpoken of <hi>Abraham,</hi> long before he had received <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> and done that Signall and Heroick Action, by which the Sincerity and Truth of his Faith was evidenced. So that the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> words cannot be underſtood, as if he intended to decide whether <hi>Faith</hi> or <hi>Works</hi> did <hi>Juſtifie;</hi> but onely that he determins what kind of <hi>Faith</hi> it was which Juſtified, <hi>viz.</hi> not a Naked and Barren, but an Effectuall and Working Faith: And that <hi>Abrahams</hi> was ſuch a kind of Faith, he manifeſted afterwards, in undertaking ſo Perillous and Dangerous a Task, meerly in obedience to Gods Command. From whence it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, that if <hi>Abraham,</hi> who is ſtiled, <hi>the Friend of God,</hi> did attain to the eſteem of being reputed <hi>Righteous before God,</hi> meerly upon the account of his Faith; then all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, whoſe higheſt commendation is onely to be the Followers and Imitators of <hi>Abraham,</hi> have no other way of obteining <hi>True Righteouſneſs,</hi> but by treading in the ſame <hi>footsteps of Faith,</hi> which the Patriark <hi>Abraham</hi> walked in: as the Apoſtle concludes,<note place="margin">Rom. 4.23, 24.</note> 
               <hi>It was not written for him, i. e.</hi> for <hi>Abraham alone, that it was imputed to him: But to us alſo, to whom it ſhall be imputed, if we believe on
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:55864:7"/> him, that raiſed up Jeſus our Lord from the Dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>2</label> The ſecond Objection againſt this Doctrine, is taken from that ſeeming Abſurdity and Contradiction, which would follow, ſhould men think of being ſaved by the Righteouſneſs of another: For as every man is to be condemned, onely for his own ſinnes; ſo it ſeems to be moſt Juſt and Equall, that every man ſhould be ſaved onely for his own Righteouſneſs: according to the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning of God himſelf, who doth not onely ſay, that the <hi>Wickedneſs of the Wicked,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 18.20.</note> but likewiſe that the <hi>Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Righteous ſhall be upon him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 2.</note>To this Objection, the Apoſtle excellently anſwers throughout the whole <hi>fifth Chapter</hi> of this Epiſtle, by drawing a <hi>parallel</hi> between <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Chriſt;</hi> who were the two great Heads and Repreſentatives of all Mankind, in their ſeverall Eſtates. Now if it ſhall appear that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> deſtroyed his Race, by the <hi>Imputation of his ſinne;</hi> then it cannot be Unreaſonable to believe, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> may ſave his Race, by the <hi>Imputation of his Righteouſneſs.</hi> But that <hi>Adam</hi> deſtroyed his Race, by the Imputation of his ſinne, appears clearly from hence, in that <hi>Death,</hi> which is the <hi>Wages of ſinne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">verſ. 14.</note> doth actually ceaze thoſe, who never Actually ſinned, and therefore could be but liable to it, onely upon the Account of Tranſmitted, Derivative and Imputed ſinne; as he Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues, <hi>Death reigned from Adam to Moſes, even over thoſe that had not ſinned after the ſimilitude of Adams Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſsion,</hi> i. e. over Infants. From whence he inferres, <hi>As by one mans diſobedience, Many</hi> (i. e. All who deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend from him by Naturall Generation) <hi>were made ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: ſo by the obedience of one man, Many</hi> (i. e. all who are related to him by Faith, and ſupernaturall Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) <hi>ſhall be made Righteous.</hi> Nay by how much <hi>Chriſt</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:55864:7"/> is a greater Perſon than <hi>Adam,</hi> (the one being <hi>formed from Earth,</hi> the other:<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.47.</note> being <hi>the Lord from Heaven</hi>) by ſo much ſhall the Obedience and Righteouſneſs of that One, more avail to Save, than the Unrighteouſneſs and Sinne of the other did to Deſtroy. And this the Apoſtle clears in two Particulars:</p>
            <p n="1">1. In Extent of the Pardon; which is <hi>to many ſinnes,</hi> whereas the Condemnation was onely <hi>for One.</hi> For, ſaith he, <hi>the Judgment,</hi> or <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Guilt was by one.</hi> i. e. Offence, to <hi>Condemnation; but the free-gift is of many Offences,</hi>
               <note place="margin">verſ. 16.</note> 
               <hi>unto Juſtification.</hi> In <hi>Adam,</hi> one ſinne, and that of the leſſer ſort, ſtiled <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>a ſlip</hi> or ſo, was ſufficient to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doe a World. But in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> Many ſins, how aggravated and circumſtanced ſoever, ſhall not be ſufficient to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy one Soul,</p>
            <p n="2">2. In the Excellence of the purchaſe: <hi>Adam,</hi> by his Sinne, purchaſed <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Damnation;</hi> which is, like a Motion down-hill, very Naturall and eaſie to be concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved: For that a Creature, ſhould die; that a Sinner, ſhould be ſentenced, may without any Difficulty be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined: But <hi>Chriſt</hi> purchaſed <hi>Life Eternall,</hi> which is like a Motion up-hill, very Hard and exceeding Difficult to be comprehended. From whence the Apoſtle concludes, that <hi>where Sinne,</hi> i. e. the Guilt or Demerit of <hi>Adams</hi> Sinne, <hi>abounded, there Grace,</hi> or the Gift of Life by <hi>Chriſt, did much more abound.</hi> The word in the Originall, ſignifies <hi>ſomething more than enough;</hi> ſomething,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> that was above and beyond what was ſufficient, to Antidote and to Expell the Contagion of <hi>Adams</hi> ſinne: Juſt as if a Man ſhould let in a Sea to cleanſe a ſink; ſo abundant was the <hi>Overflow</hi> of <hi>Chriſts Righteouſneſſe,</hi> for the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifying of thoſe Natures, which <hi>Adams</hi> ſinne had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:55864:8"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>3</label> The third and laſt Objection is conteined in the Text, and the ſenſe of it amounts to this: Some may ſay, If the Merit of <hi>Chriſts</hi> Death, doth ſo infinitely tranſcend the Demerit of <hi>Adams</hi> Sinne, as the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports; then, will it not follow from hence, that <hi>the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell</hi> will be a Rule of Strictneſs and Severity of Life, no longer; but rather ſet open a door to all manner of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety, ſince this Concluſion may eaſily be drawn: Since Gods Goodneſs is ſo Free, as well as full; ſince <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in the moſt proper acception, did <hi>die for Sinners;</hi> will it not follow, the greater Sinners we are, the more accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble we ſhall be to <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and the more Offences we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, the better will his Goodneſs in pardoning them ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear: As to run upon the Score, is the beſt way to ſet out and to adorn a Creditors <hi>Munificence. Come on then,</hi> will wicked men ſay, <hi>Let us ſinne that Grace may abound.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſw.</note>To this Odious and Unworthy Inference, which yet, ſo corrupt and diſingenuous it our Nature, moſt men are ready, not onely to Reaſon, but to Live by, the Apoſtle returns a double Anſwer:</p>
            <p n="1">1. In a Phraſe of Abhorrency, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: He ſeems, as it were, to ſtart and to bluſh at the bare mention of ſuch a ſuppoſall,; and therefore haſtily cries out, <hi>Farre be it,</hi> that any ſhould be ſuch a Wretch, as to make Rich and Undeſerved Mercy, a Motive of his Contumacy; that any ſhould therefore preſume to Offend, becauſe God is Willing to Pardon; that any ſhould therefore ſpurn their Heavenly Father on the <hi>Bowels,</hi> becauſe they are <hi>Tender</hi> and Yearn toward them: This doth not uſe to be our manner of dealing with Men, and therefore <hi>Farre be it,</hi> that any ſhould thus deal with God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He anſwers by inſtancing in the Life of Himſelf, and thoſe Believing <hi>Romanes,</hi> to whom he writes; As if he
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:55864:8"/> had ſaid, <hi>Farre be it</hi> that any ſhould make ſuch Impious Concluſions, from ſo Holy, and ſo Gracious Premiſes; that any ſhould preſume to Poiſon themſelves, becauſe there is an Antidote ſo neer them: If any doe ſo, it is their own Fault; for we have experimentally found this Doctrine of <hi>Free-Grace,</hi> to have had a clean contrary Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and Operation upon us; and inſtead of Exciting us to Sinne, even to cut up and root out in us, not onely the Acts, but even the Habit of Sinfullneſs: <hi>How then,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>ſhall we that are dead to ſinne, live any longer there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in?</hi> Which being the Full ſcope and Deſign of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles whole Diſcourſe, it affords us this uſefull Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the beſt and moſt effectuall way to mortifie the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of In-dwelling ſinne, is to conſider how free, how Abſolute, how Unconditionall Gods Grace is in pardoning it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Before I proceed to handle this, I muſt needs take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the Objection, and from thence obſerve;</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>That Corrupt and Curious Wits, doe uſually draw perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and deſtructive conſequences from the moſt Precious and ſoul-ſaving Truths.</hi> For Inſtance; What Doctrine can be more Winning, to a Deſperate; or more comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, to a Deſpairing Sinner; than to hear, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath already fully ſatisfied for Sinne; that God is <hi>willing to be reconciled;</hi> that, notwithſtanding his Greatneſs, he even woes us to be at Peace with him; and, in token of his Readineſs, he offers us Peace and Pardon, unclogged with any Condition; he requires nothing but <hi>Faith,</hi> i. e. a Naked and an Empty hand, to take what he is willing in Bounty to beſtow. Yet the Diſputer in my Text, labours to make this Sweet, appear to be very Unſound Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; and would fright men from embracing their Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diall, leſt by accident it ſhould heighten and encreaſe their
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:55864:9"/> Diſtemper, Thus it hath fared with all the Abſtruſe and moſt Myſterious Points of our Religion; the <hi>Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the eternall Sonne of God,</hi> the <hi>Reſurrection of the Body,</hi> the <hi>Aſsiſtance of the Holy Spirit in the Hearts of Believers,</hi> have been all attaqued and ſet upon by mens Irregular Fancies, and each Age hath produced ſome Sect or other, who have made themſelves Famous by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect oppoſition unto thoſe forementioned Truths. But to omit them, I ſhall content my ſelf with thoſe Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which the Apoſtle makes in this Epiſtle, <hi>Chap.</hi> 3, He layes down this Concluſion: That God in the Wiſdome of his Providence, ſo orders and manages all Events, as that out of <hi>Evill,</hi> he doth extract <hi>Good;</hi> and makes even our <hi>Unrighteouſneſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">verſ. 5.</note> to ſet off and to illuſtrate his <hi>Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs:</hi> From whence one preſently inferres, <hi>then is God unrighteous, who taketh vengeance,</hi> i. e. who puniſheth men for that, which at laſt doth redound to the Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of his Glory; and then goes on, <hi>Let us doe Evill, that good may come of it:</hi> i. e. Let us Sinne, that Gods Glory may be promoted. Which Impious Deduction, whereby Gods Providence is made to countermand his Precepts, the Apoſtle confutes in that ſharp Expreſſion, <hi>Whoſe Damnation is Juſt,</hi> i. e. ſuch who will not actively Glorifie God, by their Obedience unto his <hi>Revealed Will,</hi> God will get himſelf Glory of them, by Puniſhing their Diſobedience. Again in that Great Buſineſs of Gods <hi>Abſolute and Unconditionall Electing</hi> of ſome unto Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Life,<note place="margin">Rom. 9.</note> the Apoſtle inſtanceth in the Examples of <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> and <hi>Eſau;</hi> who, when as yet neither of them <hi>had done Good or Evill,</hi> yet one was preferred before the other; or which the Apoſtle gives no other reaſon, but this; <hi>That the Purpoſe of God, according to Election might ſtand, not of Works, but of him that calleth.</hi> Againſt which
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:55864:9"/> Unmerited and Irreſpective choice,<note place="margin">verſ. 14.</note> there is One in that place objects, <hi>Is there not then Unrighteouſneſs with God? i. e.</hi> Is not God Partiall and Unequall in his determinations concerning Man, thus to chuſe and preferre one before another, when as by Nature, All are Equall? To this he anſwers, by alleaging God's Soveraignty,<note place="margin">verſ. 15.</note> who in the caſe of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> affirms of Himſelf, <hi>I will have Mercy on whom I will have Mercy;</hi> and the Apoſtle inferres from thence, <hi>and whom he will he hardens,</hi> i. e. he ſhowes no Mercy to, but leaves them in their Naturall Hardneſs and Impenitency. And when the Objector is not ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with this, but cries out, <hi>Why doth he then find fault?</hi> i. e. why doth he reprove and ſeem Angry againſt ſinne and ſinners? <hi>for who hath reſiſted his Will?</hi> The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle then in ſtead of anſwering any further, asks a Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, which the Bold Diſputers of our times will never anſwer, and that is, <hi>Who art thou O man who diſputeſt againſt God?</hi> by which way of Procedure, he ſufficiently ſhews, that in the opening of Divine Miſteries, nothing is more hard, than to ſtop a Diſputers mouth. And the Reaſons are</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> Firſt, Becauſe Men doe uſually ſound the Depths of God, by a very Falſe and Imperfect Line; and that is, by <hi>Naturall Reaſon:</hi> There is indeed a Reaſon given to man, which is capaable of the Higheſt Miſteries; this in Philoſophy, is called <hi>Right;</hi> in Scripture, <hi>Enlightned Reaſon;</hi> i. e. ſuch a Reaſon as ſtoops and ſubmits to Faith, and dares believe God in ſpight of all contrary ſuggeſtions. But all the while our Reaſon, is in its Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and Unreclaimed eſtate, <hi>like a Bullock unaccuſtomed to the Yoke,</hi> it kicks at every thing which it cannot com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend. Thus even the moſt Holy men, while they did quit their ſafe Rule, which is Gods own manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:55864:10"/> of his Wayes in Scripture, and ventured in their own Reaſons to argue about Divine Providence;<note place="margin">Pſal. 73. Jer. 12. Hab. 1.</note> the <hi>Proſperity of the Wicked,</hi> was ſo Obvious, and withall ſo Great an Objection, that they were unable to reſolve it; as appears by the Complaints and Inquietudes of <hi>David, Jeremy, Habakuk,</hi> and others upon this Subject. That alone which ſilenced <hi>Job,</hi> in the midſt of his bold Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulations, did likewiſe ſatisfie them; and that was, a diſtinct and clear Diſcovery of <hi>Gods uncontrolable Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty and Dominion over all his Creatures;</hi> which ought to be admired at a diſtance by us, and not too cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly pried into, leaſt ſo Wonderfull and Amazing an Object doe ſtrike us Blind. Thoſe Tenets, wherein Gods Honour is mainly concerned, ſuch are, His managing of all Events,<note place="margin">Act. 1.16. &amp; 3.28.</note> even the Sinnes of Man (as the Scripture tells us he did <hi>pre-ordain the Treachery of Judas</hi>) with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Imputation to his Holineſs: His diſpoſing of all Perſons, abſolutely to their reſpective Ends, and without any Imputation to his Juſtice—Such things as theſe, the Apoſtle hath taught us to call <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Untraceable Paths,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom 11.33.</note> in which onely an Humbled Soul can walk. Here if we will goe, we muſt goe groveling, with our <hi>Faces in the Duſt,</hi> leaſt if, like <hi>Moſes,</hi> we draw neer to pry with too much curioſity, his <hi>Dread doe fall upon us, and his Terrors make us afraid.</hi> Till Humane Wiſdome be throughly abaſed, and all the Pride of Earthly Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge be purged out, the more we ſtrive to underſtand <hi>the things of God,</hi> the more we are entangled; till at laſt we come, not onely to Reject, but likewiſe to Revile them.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> The ſecond Reaſon is, Becauſe men are not onely Shallow in their Apprehenſions, but Raſh and Haſty in their Concluſions: We are Naturally of Proud Impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:55864:10"/> Spirits, and apt to range abroad, in queſt, not of Truth, but, as thoſe at <hi>Athens, of ſomething that is New;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 17.</note> without purſuing thoſe firm grounds, whereupon to bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom and to fix a Perſwaſion. It is therefore the moſt common cauſe of all Practicall Errors in the World, that Men doe uſually faſten upon that part of a Tenet, which favours them in their Luſts, without taking notice of the whole Compaſs and Latitude of it. Thus when a Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner hears that <hi>God is Mercifull,</hi> he preſently cries out, This is good News for me, for I am already, and reſolve ſtill to be a Sinner; never conſidering, that <hi>Mercy leads to Repentance;</hi> and it can no farther be pleaded, or pretended to by any, then as it doth influence us to return from Sinne to God. So perhaps ſome may argue, <hi>If I am predeſtined to be ſaved, I ſhall be ſaved;</hi> and what need I then trouble my ſelf with Holineſs? Whereas the <hi>End</hi> is never deſigned by God, but with Reſpect of and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordination to the <hi>Means:</hi> And all the ſeverall Stages in our Journey to Heaven, are appointed in the ſame Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Regiſter, wherein the place it ſelf is deſigned for us. In ſhort, as in a Chain, when men catch haſtily at the Link that is next them, without taking notice of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexion and ſeries whereby many are joyned together, the whole chain is apt thereby to be diſordered and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compoſed: ſo is it in Divine Truths, if we look not at the whole contexture of them, and that admirable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance which each part hath upon the other; we are apt to be led away by our own Prejudices, and to draw Abſurd and Monſtrous Conſequences, which, had we leaſure to take a View of the Whole Body of Sacred Truth, we ſhould not have adventured to doe. Herein mainly conſiſts the Difference between <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Error:</hi> Error is then ſtrongeſt, when it is conſidered Single;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:55864:11"/> but the ſtrength of Truth lies in its ſtanding linked and confederated unto other Doctrines: Therefore to ſingle out any one Opinion, how true ſoever, and handle it apart, is, like the cutting of <hi>Sampſons</hi> Hair, it makes it leſs ſtrong, and more liable to miſ-conſtruction: It robs it not onely of its Strength, but likewiſe of its Beauty.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
               </label> The Uſe hence is to Adviſe all, not to judge of any Opinion or Party of Men, by thoſe Prejudices wherewith they are loaded, or by thoſe Ill-favoured Conſequences which may be wreſted from their Doctrine; but let us labour to diſcern every thing, as it ſhines in its own Light, by the clearneſs of Scripture-diſcovery: All Truth, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially Divine, muſt be tried by its Evidence, and not by its Conſequences. When we have tired out our ſelves and others with needleſs Objections, one <hi>Scriptum eſt,</hi> wherewith our Saviour anſwered the Devill, with ſtand like a Rock, and abide all thoſe Waves of Oppoſition, which don't ſo much Batter Scripture, as Daſh and Break themſelves upon it. And if ever this Advice were neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, certainly this Age, wherein we live, doth moſt of all require it; in which, whatever may leſſen and undervalue Scripture is let in and broken looſe upon us. For what by <hi>Humane Additions,</hi> on the one ſide; and by Pretences to more <hi>Immediate Revelations</hi> on the other; the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, which is the <hi>undoubted Word of God,</hi> is robbed of its Sufficiency and Perfection; and harder Conditions are required of us, for the attaining of Eternall Life, than thoſe which our Saviour hath enjoyned us, <hi>viz.</hi> To Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and to Obey him alone. Let us therefore bring both our own, and all other mens Opinions, unto this Touchſtone; and when we have found a <hi>Sic dixit Deus, the Mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it,</hi> for any thing in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, let us ſtick to that Declaration, without ever
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:55864:11"/> troubling our ſelves with Conſequences, which are but ſo much Duſt thrown in our Eyes, to keep us from diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning our Duty. Should we ever quit this hold, I can ſee nothing before me but <hi>Sea</hi> and <hi>Aire,</hi> i. e. a Wide and Endleſs Labyrinth of Inextricable Error: But while we ſtick faſt to this Rule, we may indeed erre in the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> but we are ſure the <hi>Text</hi> is <hi>Infallible.</hi> And the more Submiſs and Silent our Reaſon is, in things which may at firſt bluſh appear Strange and Contradictory, the more, I will not ſay Meritorious, but Pleaſing and Accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table is our Obedience.</p>
            <p>Having thus diſpatched that Obſervation which the Objection in my Text did lead me to, I come now to the Doctrine which I firſt raiſed, and which takes in the whole Scope and Deſign of the Apoſtles arguing, <hi>viz. That the Beſt and moſt Effectuall Way to mortifie the power of Indwelling Sinue, is rightly to conſider how Free, Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute and Unconditionall, Gods Grace is in pardoning it.</hi> In which there are theſe three Points to be explained.</p>
            <p n="1">1<hi rend="sup">o</hi> That, <hi>Gods Grace in pardoning Sinne, is Abſolute, Free and Unconditionall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſerv. </seg>2</label> 2<hi rend="sup">o</hi> That, <hi>A Conſiderate and fixed Belief of this, is the beſt way to mortifie the Power of Indwelling Sinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3c That, <hi>A Believer, muſt never think he hath arrived to the Truth of his Profeſsion, till Sinne is mortified in him: or,</hi> in the Apoſtles words, <hi>Till he is dead to Sinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>1</label> The firſt Point is, That, <hi>Gods Grace in pardoning Sinne, is Abſolute, Free and Unconditionall.</hi> I mean, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting nothing in, requiring nothing from the creature, as that which may merit and deſerve ſuch Favour. Thus all the Promiſes run, <hi>I will take them,</hi> ſaith God ſpeaking of the New Covenant or Goſpell-Times, <hi>to be my People,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:55864:12"/> and I will be their God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 31.33.</note> 
               <hi>For I will Forgive their Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and I will remember their Sinnes no more.</hi> So ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſame Covenant by the Prophet <hi>Ezekiell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 36.25.</note> 
               <hi>I will,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>ſprinkle clean water upon you, and from all your Filthineſs will I cleanſe you.</hi> Which gracious Promiſe, leaſt it ſhould ſeem to reſpect any thing in them as meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouſly exciting it, God doth expreſly premiſe, <hi>I doe not this for your ſake,</hi>
               <note place="margin">verſ. 22.</note> 
               <hi>O houſe of Iſrael, but for my ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Names ſake.</hi> And again concludes it thus; <hi>Not for your ſakes doe I this,</hi>
               <note place="margin">verſ. 32.</note> 
               <hi>ſaith the Lord God, be it known unto you.</hi> Therefore in that Form of Words, which God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes unto <hi>Returning Backſliders,</hi> he commands them to ſay,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 14.2.</note> 
               <hi>Lord take away all Iniquity, and receive us graciouſly.</hi> To which God preſently replies,<note place="margin">verſ. 4.</note> 
               <hi>I will heal their Back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlidings, I will love them Freely.</hi> But beſides what may be deduced from the whole Tenour and Current of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture-Promiſes, this will yet farther appear from theſe three Conſiderations:</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> Firſt, From the Nature of God who pardons Sinne, who cannot be moved or altered by any condition in the Creature, ſince he himſelf is the ſole Author and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtower of whatever good condition the Creature is able to perform. For according to the Queſtion of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 11.33.</note> 
               <hi>Who hath first given unto him, and it ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenced to him again?</hi> or, as the words are in <hi>Job,</hi> from whence the Apoſtle took them,<note place="margin">Job 41.11.</note> 
               <hi>Who hath prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me,</hi> ſc. by doing for me, <hi>that I ſhould repay him?</hi> Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by intimating, that none hath or is able ſo to doe any thing for God, as that he ſhould thereby challenge any thing from him, by way of Recompence: As the words following in that place imply, For <hi>whatever is under the whole Heaven is mine.</hi> When therefore the Holy Men doe begge pardon of Sinne, their finall reſort is to Gods
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:55864:12"/> Mercy or Power; as <hi>Moſes</hi> when he intercedes for <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael; And now let the Power of my Lord be great,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb 14.17.</note> 
               <hi>accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as thou haſt ſpoken, ſaying, the Lord is long ſuffering and of great Mercy, forgiving Iniquity and Tranſgreſſion.</hi> And ſo he goes on, <hi>Forgive I pray thee the Iniquity of this People, according to the greatneſs of thy Mercy.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mic. 7.18.19.</note> So the Prophet <hi>Micah, Who is a God like unto thee, that pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Iniquity, and paſſeth by the Tranſgreſſion of the Rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of his Heritage, becauſe he delighteth in Mercy.</hi> Whereas did conſideration of any thing in the Creature, move God to ſhew Compaſſion; Forgiveneſs from him, would no longer be <hi>Grace</hi> but <hi>Debt;</hi> and God in pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sinne, would not exert an act of <hi>Power,</hi> but an act of <hi>Juſtice:</hi> and Men might challenge not onely Pardon of Sinne, but likewiſe, Heaven it ſelf, as a Reward of their Performances. Which is quite contrary to the whole Current of Scripture, and to all thoſe Conceptions, which the Majeſty and Greatneſs of God, together with the Vileneſs and Deſpicable meanneſs of the Creature, muſt needs enforce upon all Rationall and Conſiderate Men. Since therefore the Promiſes of God run Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely, ſince the Nature of God is Inalterably, <hi>i. e.</hi> Freely Gracious; they neither conſult Gods Honour, nor the Comfort of doubting Chriſtians, who interpoſe the Clog of any preceding Condition. They are very unfaithfull Embaſſadours to the King of Heaven, who ſtreighten their Commiſſion; and ſpeak Peace and Pardon in Terms leſs generall, than they have received.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> Secondly, This will appear yet farther from Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the Price, which was paid for Sinne. For though God pardons ſinne <hi>Freely,</hi> in reference to us, ſince we neither did nor could deſerve it; yet it was not Free in reference to our <hi>Surety;</hi> by Chriſt this was dearly
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:55864:13"/> bought, and whatever we enjoy thereof, was firſt ſealed, and comes down ſtreaming to us, in the <hi>Blood of the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator.</hi> Now to know the Greatneſs of the Price, the beſt way will be to conſider the Greatneſs of the Perſon, who paid it.<note place="margin">Joh. 1.</note> In the beginning of <hi>Johns</hi> Goſpell, we read of one, whom he there ſtiles <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, i. e. <hi>Reaſon</hi> or the <hi>Eternall ſpring of Wiſdome,</hi> of him it is ſaid, <hi>that he was with God,</hi> nay <hi>that he was God;</hi> and <hi>as God did make the World.</hi> If we look a little farther, we ſhall find that this very Perſon, this <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, i. e. <hi>became Fleſh,</hi> or <hi>frail Man,</hi> and laying aſide the Glory of his Divinity for a time <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Tabernacled,</hi> or <hi>pitched his Tent</hi> among the ſonnes of Men. It was this <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, this <hi>aſſumed Nature</hi> of his, which he ſacrificed as a Victim to appeaſe his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Anger, and to expiate the ſinnes of the world; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as he ſpeaks himſelf. <hi>The Bread that I will give you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 6.51.</note> 
               <hi>is my Fleſh,</hi> or <hi>my Humane Nature, which I will give for the Life of the World.</hi> Where by <hi>World</hi> is not, nor cannot be meant, the <hi>Generality of Man-kind,</hi> of which the greateſt part periſh, which could not poſſibly be, had Chriſt actually ſhed his Blood for them: but, as our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour explains himſelf in another place,<note place="margin">Joh. 10. &amp;c. 11. v. 52.</note> 
               <hi>His Sheep,</hi> or <hi>the Generality of Believers</hi> ſcattered throughout the world: ſo that the word <hi>World,</hi> is of the ſame Extent with the word <hi>Many,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 20.28.</note> which our Saviour elſe-where uſeth. As in <hi>Matthew,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Mat. 26.28.</note> 
               <hi>the Sonne of Man came to give his life a Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome for,</hi> or, <hi>in ſtead of many.</hi> And afterward, <hi>This is the Blood of the New Covenant, which was ſhed for Many, for Remiſsion of Sinnes.</hi> That we may know the ineſtimable value of this Blood, it is called by the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> and that without a Figure <hi>the Blood of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 20.28.</note> i. e. which the Sonne of God ſhed in that Humane Nature, which he had united unto himſelf. Who is there then that will not
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:55864:13"/> think ſuch Blood ſufficient Ranſome? For as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle argues excellently,<note place="margin">Heb. 9.13.</note> 
               <hi>If the Blood of Bulls and Goats ſanctifies to the purifying of the Fleſh; How much more ſhall the Blood of Chriſt, who through the Eternall Spirit, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered himſelf up to God, purge our Conſcience from Dead Works,</hi> i. e. Cleanſe our Souls both from the Leproſie and Guilt of Sinne? So that to eek out this Sacrifice, by mingling with it any Vain Oblations of our own, is nothing elſe but to leſſen its value, as they, who light up their Candles at noon-day, doe onely Affront and Prejudice the ſplendour of the Sunne. When ſuch a Price is already paid, for any to appear Nice and Dainty, to cry out they are not Humbled, not Sorrowfull, not Thankfull Enough, and therefore neglect to make uſe of it, this is nothing elſe, but either Peeviſhly, to refuſe offered Comfort; or elſe Proudly, to think we are able by our delay to make our ſelves worthy of it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>3</label> Thirdly, The laſt Argument may be taken from the Impoſſibility there is, that we ſhould be able to perform any thing acceptably unto God, till we are come within the Terms of the Covenant; Then are we within the Covenant on Gods part, when we have accepted it on ours: but till then, we are under the Law, all our Works are Legall Works, and our <hi>Repentance it ſelf is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of;</hi> as being infinitely ſhort of that Perfection which the Law requires. Beſides, upon ſuppoſition that ſuch a meaſure of <hi>Humiliation, Sorrow, Contrition,</hi> or other ſuch like Acts, were prerequired to capacitate and make us fit for the receiving of our Pardon; what infinite diſquiets muſt this needs beget in every Sinner, that is now upon the point of his Converſion; for who ſhall be able to fix a juſt Proportion? or aſſuredly tell him, that he hath grieved and mourned enough? ſince there
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:55864:14"/> can be no Proportion between our Sinne and our Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and likewiſe our Bodies may be waſted with Grief, and our Eyes fail us with weeping, and yet all our Fears, prove onely an Idle and a Fruitleſs Expence, as <hi>Cains</hi> and <hi>Judas</hi> did. There can be therefore no better or more warrantable Advice be given unto a poor lamenting Creature, than to bid him leave off his Works, and throw himſelf immediately into the Arms of Mercy: ſince who ſo reſts upon his own Endeavours, labours in the very Fire, and undertakes a Task beyond his manage, in thinking to Fit himſelf for Mercy; whereas it muſt be Mercy, already in ſome meaſure apprehended, which muſt qualifie and fit us for the receiving more.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>1</label> Againſt this it may be objected, That the Promiſe in the Goſpell runs,<note place="margin">Mar. 16.</note> 
               <hi>He that believeth, ſhall be ſaved;</hi> and the Command by the Apoſtle is,<note place="margin">Acts 3, 19.</note> 
               <hi>Repent that your ſinnes may be blotted out.</hi> From whence it may be gathered, that <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Repentance</hi> are required as Conditions to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion; and that Pardon of Sinne is not ſo Abſolute on Gods part, but that ſtill ſomething muſt be done on ours, to qualifie us for the receiving it. But I anſwer</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſw.</note>1. For <hi>Repentance,</hi> that is no diſtinct and ſeparate condition of it ſelf, becauſe it alwayes follows Faith, and can no more be ſevered from it, than Motion from Life: whence it is that the Apoſtles doe promiſcuouſly uſe one for the other; as <hi>Peter,</hi> to thoſe who were wrought on by his Sermon, and came to him for Direction, he bids them <hi>Repent;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 2.37.</note> but <hi>Paul,</hi> to the Jaylor who was in the ſame caſe, he commands him to <hi>Believe;</hi> and our Saviour joyns them both together, in that Epitome of his firſt Sermon, <hi>Repent and believe the Goſpell:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mar. 1.13.</note> thereby intimating that one could not be without the other.—Therefore</p>
            <p n="2">2. Though <hi>Faith</hi> be required as a Condition to the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:55864:14"/> receiving of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and Pardon by him, yet it is ſuch a Condition, as takes nothing at all from the Freeneſs of Gods Gift; no more than Emptying the Hand, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king an Almes, doth leſſen his Bounty that beſtowes it. For <hi>Faith</hi> is nothing elſe but a Naked Hand, and hath no influence at all upon Gods Gift, to make it more or leſs Free; but all its influence is downwards, by applying and appropriating of that Gift, to make it Ours. And therefore in Scripture-language, to <hi>Believe in Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>to Receive Him,</hi> is the ſame thing: As <hi>John</hi> ſpeaks,<note place="margin">Joh. 1.12.</note> 
               <hi>As many as received him, to them he gave power to become the ſonnes of God, even to as many as believe on his Name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As a Medicine may be given <hi>gratis</hi> by a Phyſician, he may ask nothing for it, yet except the ſick-man take it, it will not cure him: So God offers <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Mercy</hi> freely, but unleſs we <hi>Believe</hi> i. e. <hi>Receive</hi> him, he will not profit us. And in this, and no other ſenſe is Faith a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. But</p>
            <p n="3">3. Even in this ſignification, as Faith ſignifies not a power of Acting, but meerly a power of Accepting, yet ſo it is a Condition, onely of Gods beſtowing, and not of Mans procuring. Thus our Saviour:<note place="margin">Joh. 6.44. verſ. 35.</note> 
               <hi>None can come unto me</hi> (i. e. <hi>believe on me,</hi> as he there explains) <hi>except the Father which hath ſent me draw him.</hi> And again, <hi>He that hath heard, and learned of the Father, he cometh unto me;</hi> ſo, <hi>No man can come unto me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">verſ. 45.</note> 
               <hi>except it were given to him of my Father.</hi> All which places ſhow, that <hi>Faith,</hi> which is <hi>a coming to Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">verſ. 64.</note> is not wrought in any but peculiar Power and Influence of God. And accordingly, the Apoſtle <hi>Paul, By Grace,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>are ye ſaved,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.8.</note> 
               <hi>through Faith, and that not of your ſelves, it is the Gift of God,</hi> i. e. That Faith by which ye are enabled to receive Chriſt, is as much the Gift of God, as Chriſt himſelf who is received
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:55864:15"/> by it. Therefore he prayes, that they may be ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened <hi>by the Spirit of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">c. 3.16, 17.</note> 
               <hi>in the Inner Man,</hi> that ſo, <hi>Chriſt might dwell in their Hearts by Faith:</hi> intimating, that, without ſuch Supernaturall Aſſiſtance, they neither could nor would Believe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>2</label> Againſt this it may be objected again, If God alone gives Faith, why then are we commanded to <hi>Believe</hi> and to <hi>Repent,</hi> for this preſuppoſes a Power in the Creature to Obey, or elſe the Command would be in vain.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſw.</note>I anſwer, That Gods command doth not alwayes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſe a Power already exiſting in the Creature, but being a Word from God, it gives that Power which was not there before. As when God ſaid, <hi>Let there be Light,</hi> there was no activity in that Dark <hi>Chaos,</hi> ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient of it ſelf to produce it, but God by his Word at the ſame time created what he did command. To which Action of Gods, the Apoſtle compares his bringing any to the Knowledg of Chriſt;<note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.6.</note> 
               <hi>God,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Light to ſhine out of Darkneſs, hath ſhone into our Hearts, to give unto us the Knowledg of his Glory in the Face of Chriſt.</hi> So in the New Teſtament, when our Saviour commanded <hi>the Sea to be ſtill, the Blind to See, the Dead to Riſe,</hi> &amp;c. there was no Ability in thoſe Creature to Obey his Commands; but his Command, going out with Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Authority, gave unto them Power: ſo when the Miniſters of the Goſpell command Sinners <hi>to Believe,</hi> and <hi>to Repent,</hi> the word goes out in the Name and in the Strength of God, and, whereever it is effectuall, it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veighs that Power, which was not there before. And this is it, which makes <hi>Preaching</hi> neceſſary unto the worlds end, becauſe the Spirit of God doth cooperate with it; as the Apoſtle hath it, when he commands a Miniſter to be Meek, and ready to Teach even thoſe that ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:55864:15"/> to oppoſe the Truth: <hi>if,</hi> ſaith he,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.24.</note> 
               <hi>peradventure God will give them Repentance:</hi> We Preach to, and Pray for Sinners, onely with a <hi>Peradventure;</hi> perhaps, God may work ſome good by us: but if God doth not work, our Words cannot, and the Sinner himſelf will not.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
               </label> This may ſerve to teach all thoſe, who begin to be troubled for their paſt Sinnes, which way they muſt take to arrive unto Comfort and ſatisfaction. There are ſome Ignorant and Unskilfull Phyſicians of the Soul, who preſcribe <hi>Faſting, Pennance, Uneaſie Poſtures of Prayer,</hi> and the like, which are at the beſt but <hi>Bodily exerciſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.</note> which Profits little, becauſe it reacheth not to the Core of Sinne, that lies within. Such kind of Methods as theſe, doe onely prune and lop the Branches of Corruption, but leave the Root entire; Men may in a needleſs Rigour ſtarve their Bodies, and all the while doe nothing elſe but feed their Pride. My advice rather is, to a diſconſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late Sinner, that he would preſently lay hold upon his Pardon: And my grounds for this Advice are theſe two.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Motive </seg>1</label> 1. Nothing doth more engage us in a Wilfull and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberate Courſe of Sinning than Deſpair of Pardon. When once <hi>Cain</hi> cries out,<note place="margin">Gen. 4.</note> that his <hi>Sinne was greater than could be forgiven;</hi> the next News we hear of him, is, That <hi>he went out from the Preſence of the Lord.</hi> Thus when God ſummoned the People by his Prophet <hi>Jeremy;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 18.12.</note> to <hi>return from the Evill of their Wayes,</hi> he brings them in ſaying, <hi>There is no Hope;</hi> and then it preſently follows, <hi>but we will walk in the Imagination of our own Hearts.</hi> The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Peter</hi> therefore exhorting thoſe to whom he writes, to make a Progreſs in Holineſs, by adding one Grace to another,— <hi>But he,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>who wants theſe things is blind,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.9.</note> 
               <hi>forgetting that he was cleanſed from his old ſinnes;</hi> thereby intimating, that as Preſumption begets Confidence, ſo
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:55864:16"/> Deſpair begets Careleſneſs in Sinning. As we read of ſome, <hi>who have died for fear of Death;</hi> ſo is it in this caſe, when men dare ſo much wrong Gods goodneſs, as to imagin, that he will not make good his Promiſe to them, though it runs Indefinitely, they runne ſo farre in Sinne, till at laſt they dare not think of Returning; which ſeems to have been <hi>Davids</hi> caſe, when he cries out, <hi>Innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Evils have compaſſed me about, mine Iniquities have taken hold upon me, ſo that I am not able to look up, they are more than the hairs of my head, therefore my heart fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth me.</hi> While he ſtayed and forbore to paſs the <hi>Ford</hi> which Mercy had ſhallowed for him, his Sinnes like a Torrent, began to overwhelme him with horror and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazement.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Motive </seg>2</label> 2. Pardon of Sinne—for the time paſt, and Power againſt Sinne for the time to come, goe both together. As when a Judge doth free a Priſoner, at the ſame time he gives him Liberty, he knocks off his Chains; ſo when God intends to doe good unto a Sinner, he <hi>never ſevers his Gifts,</hi> but compleats the work of his Redemption, by Purifying and ſtrengthening Grace at the ſame time. As he ſpeaks by the Prophet,<note place="margin">Ezek. 36.</note> 
               <hi>I will ſprinkle clean water upon you, and ye ſhall be clean:</hi> then he preſently adds, <hi>A new heart alſo will I give you, and I will put my Spirit within you, and cauſe you to walk in my wayes, and you ſhall keep my Judgments and doe them.</hi> And the reaſon of this is clear, becauſe when a Sinner hath once received his Pardon, he may boldly goe to God and Chriſt, and by Prayer engage their Power in his behalf; but till then, he is not able to doe any thing; he cannot pray in Faith, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath no Aſſurance that he ſhall be heard; he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not act in Faith, becauſe he hath no Promiſe that he ſhall be aſſiſted; but when once he hath taken, what God
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:55864:16"/> offers, he hath a certainty of both.</p>
            <p>But ſome may object, That were their Sinnes leſs,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Object.</note> then there was ſome Hope; but their Sinnes have been ſo many, and ſo ſtrangely aggravated, that they muſt needs ſit down under the ſorrow, as being in an hopeleſs condition.</p>
            <p>For anſwer, I wiſh all thoſe who make this Objection,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſw.</note> (as indeed none ever thinks of returning to God but <hi>he meets with this Lion in his way</hi>) would ſeriouſly ask, whether they find themſelves as Willing to forſake their Sinnes, as they pretend to be ſorry for them. And if they doe, then let them conſider theſe three things:</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Latitude and Extent of Chriſts Death; I doe not mean as to the Univerſality of the Perſons (for I find no ground for that) but as to the Qualifications of thoſe for whom Chriſt died: And we ſhall find it was for <hi>Sinners,</hi> for the <hi>Ungodly,</hi> for <hi>Enemies;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 5.6, 8, 10</note> from whence a Repenting Sinner may thus argue; If Chriſt died for Sinners, then certainly he will not refuſe me becauſe I have been a Sinner: If he died for Enemies, then ſure he will not caſt me off, if I am ready to lay down my Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, and be reconciled unto him. This was it which comforted <hi>Paul, It is,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>a Faithfull ſaying,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.15.</note> 
               <hi>that Christ came to die for Sinners; among which I am chief:</hi> he confeſſes as much Guilt, as could poſſibly ſtick to him, and yet takes comfort in that generall Truth, that Chriſt <hi>came to die for Sinners:</hi> And then propoſes his own Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, <hi>For this cauſe I obtained Mercy, that in me firſt Jeſus Chriſt might ſhew forth all long-ſuffering, for a pattern to them which ſhould hereafter believe on him to life everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting.</hi> We muſt take heed how we fruſtrate the Grace of God, for, as the Apoſtle argues, <hi>If Righteouſneſs,</hi> or <hi>Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication had been by the Law, then had Chriſt died in vain:</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:55864:17"/> So if Sinners, who are deſirous above all things to come unto Chriſt, ſhould therefore be driven out from him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have been Sinners, then would <hi>Chriſt have died in vain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Conſider the Freeneſs and Liberality of the Invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation: There is no condition ſo ſad, but there is ſome word of Invitation or other, which particularly concerns that condition:<note place="margin">Prov. 9.4, 5. Iſa. 55.1. Mat. 11.29. Rev. 22.17.</note> The <hi>Fooliſh and ſimple,</hi> in <hi>Proverbs:</hi> The <hi>Hungry and Thirſty,</hi> in <hi>Iſay:</hi> The <hi>Weary and Heavy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laden,</hi> in <hi>Matthew;</hi> and, which is beyond all, <hi>Whoever will,</hi> in the <hi>Revelations; Whoever will, let him come and drink of the Water of Life freely.</hi> There cannot be any thing more free and more inviting than this, that whoever will, may be ſure of Well-come, I doe not ſay, that any Man hath this will of or from himſelf; but this I ſay, that he who hath a <hi>Will,</hi> hath a <hi>Warrant;</hi> and may boldly come to Chriſt, and claim the benefit of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe. Eſpecially ſince Juſtification dependeth not at all upon our Working, but upon our Willing; as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle hath it, <hi>to him that worketh not</hi> (that is, that bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no meritorious works along with him) <hi>but believeth on him that juſtifies the Ungodly, his Faith is counted for Righteouſneſs,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, Conſider the Tender and the Compaſſionate Nature of Chriſt, how he never refuſed any that came unto him: And therefore <hi>Lepers,</hi> the <hi>Blind</hi> and <hi>Lame, Publicans</hi> and <hi>Sinners</hi> had on earth moſt both of his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and Power: The ſame Promiſes which, brought them, he hath left to encourage us—when he ſayes—<hi>Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one that my Father giveth me will come unto me;</hi> and <hi>He that cometh to me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 6.37.</note> 
               <hi>I will in no wiſe caſt out.</hi> He that ſaith of himſelf, <hi>He came,</hi> not onely to <hi>ſave,</hi> but likewiſe, to <hi>ſeek that which was loſt;</hi> will not be harſh to any, who
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:55864:17"/> are now upon the point of returning to him. Hence we read that <hi>Peter,</hi> who denied; <hi>Paul,</hi> who perſecuted; the three thouſand in the <hi>Acts,</hi> who crucified him, were all up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Repentance received by him. Our Saviour hath the ſame Bowels ſtill, and though he hath changed his Place, yet he hath not changed his Nature;<note place="margin">Heb. 4.15, 16.</note>—<hi>Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,</hi> in the Apoſtles words, <hi>ſince we have not an High-Prieſt, which cannot be touched with our infirmities: Let us come with boldneſs unto the Throne of Grace, that we may obtain Mercy, and find Grace to help in a time of Need.</hi> And ſo much for the firſt Point.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> The ſecond Point to be handled was this; That, <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more effectuall to mortifie the power of In-dwelling Sinne, than to conſider how Free and Abſolute Gods Grace is in pardoning it.</hi> By <hi>Free</hi> here, that I may repeat what I mentioned a little before, I doe not mean <hi>Free,</hi> as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding <hi>Christ,</hi> in conſideration of whom, God is thus Free to Pardon (as the expreſſions run,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.19.</note> 
               <hi>God was in Chriſt reconciling the World unto himſelf.</hi> And,<note place="margin">Rom. 3.24.</note> 
               <hi>We are juſtified freely by his Grace, through the Redemption that is in Jeſus.</hi> And, <hi>In whom,</hi> i. e. in Chriſt, <hi>we have redemption through his Blood, the forgiveneſs of Sinnes, according to the Riches of his Grace.</hi> But I mean <hi>Free,</hi> as excluding our ſelves, or any thing we can doe, either as a <hi>Cauſe</hi> procuring, or as a <hi>Condition</hi> qualifying us for receiving this Grace. In this ſenſe, that the Freeneſs of Gods Grace, is the beſt way to mortifie the Power of In-dwelling Sinne, will appear
<list>
                  <item>1. From Inſtances.</item>
                  <item>2. From Reaſon.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. For Inſtances; here is one occurres in the Text, <hi>How ſhall we,</hi> i. e. Believers, <hi>who are dead to Sinne, live any longer therein?</hi> i. e. In us, this Doctrine, being rightly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, hath wrought to the killing of Sinne; ſince we
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:55864:18"/> now learn how much we are indebted to Chriſt, and therefore ſomething muſt be done to expreſs our Thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullneſs; which he proſecutes throughout the following Chapter; and uſes an Argument to draw them off from ſinning, which at firſt ſight may ſeem Harſh and Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent, but indeed is moſt demonſtrably efficacious: Ye ſhall not ſinne, or <hi>ſinne ſhall not have dominion over you; for ye are not under the Law</hi> (which like <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Task-maſters, requires the whole tale of Brick, and allows no ſtraw) <hi>but ye are under Grace</hi> (ye now ſtand in thoſe termes with God, that he gives ſtrength, and accepts of what you doe in proportion to that Ability which he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtows) and for this Reaſon <hi>Sinne ſhall not have dominion over you.</hi> So again the Apoſtle in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians,</hi> handling the ſame ſubject, he layes down this Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition,<note place="margin">Gal. 2.16.</note> 
               <hi>That a man is not juſtified by the Works of the Law, but by the Faith of Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> Againſt which he brings an Objection, <hi>But if,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>while we ſeek to be justified by Jeſus Chriſt, we our ſelves alſo are found ſinners, is therefore Chriſt the Miniſter of ſinne?</hi> i. e. If we, who profeſs to be juſtified by Chriſt alone, doe notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſinne daily, will it not thence follow, that this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine makes men careleſs, as if thereby they might take occaſion to ſinne more freely. To this the Apoſtle an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers as he doth here, firſt <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Farre be it!</hi> and then he urgeth to the contrary his own example— <hi>I am crucified together with Chriſt;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 6.14.</note> and in another place, <hi>Farre be it, that I ſhould glory in any thing ſave in the Croſs of Chriſt, by which the World is crucified unto me, and I unto the World.</hi> And what he affirms of himſelf, we find him, in another place, aſcribing unto all Believers—of <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>— <hi>They who are Chriſts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5.24.</note> i. e. who by Faith have received and are united to him; <hi>have crucified the Fleſh,</hi> (i. e. their
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:55864:18"/> corrupt and ſinfull Nature) <hi>with the Affections and Luſts, i. e.</hi> have rooted up as it were the very Fibres and leſſer particles, by which ſinne was faſtned and incorporated into them. And the Reaſon of this is clear—</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
               </label> Becauſe, He who is once truly <hi>in Christ,</hi> i. e. who hath rightly apprehended him, forthwith becomes <hi>a New crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> as the Apoſtle argues; <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſaith he,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.15, 17</note> 
               <hi>died for All</hi> i. e. Believers, <hi>that they which live, ſhould not henceforth live unto themſelves, but unto him which died for them:</hi> From whence he inferres, <hi>Therefore if any man be in Chriſt be is a New Creature:</hi> i. e. he is altogether another kind of perſon than he was before. What the meaning of thoſe words <hi>New Creature</hi> are, will beſt appear, by comparing two places of Scripture together: In one place it is,<note place="margin">Gal. 6.15.</note> 
               <hi>In Chriſt Jeſus neither Circumciſion availeth any thing, nor Uncircumciſion, but a New Creature;</hi> which in another place runs, <hi>In Jeſus Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5.6.</note> 
               <hi>neither Circumciſion availeth any thing, nor Uncircumciſion, but Faith which worketh by Love.</hi> From whence it appears, that, in the Apoſtles ſenſe, to be <hi>a New Creature,</hi> is nothing elſe, but to have a <hi>Faith working by Love,</hi> which, our old Nature, is no more capable of, than Darkneſs is of Light; but as ſoon as ever the Spirit of God begets Faith in the Heart of any, that Faith preſently produceth Love, as Fire be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets Heat, and then Love enflames and quickens to Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. As the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> found it in himſelf, when he ſayes, <hi>The Love of Chriſt conſtrains us;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.14.</note> ſince none can apprehend ſuch an Exceſs and Overflow of Undeſerved Love, but muſt needs think himſelf obliged to return all Acts of Love, whereby he may expreſs his complacency in, and deſire of a ſtreighter Union. As the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> argues, <hi>we love him,</hi> i. e. God, <hi>becauſe he loved us firſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Joh. 4 19.</note> Since then our Lord <hi>Chriſt</hi> is pleaſed with nothing more, then
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:55864:19"/> with the <hi>Crucifying of thoſe Luſts,</hi> and Mortifying of thoſe Sinnes for which he died, it muſt needs follow from hence, that every Believer, and therein a Lover of Chriſt, will find himſelf ſenſibly ſtirred with the Hatred of Sinne, as often as he reflects upon the death of Chriſt; as men uſe to deteſt and abhorre the ſight of thoſe Weapons by which their Friends were Murdered. For ſince every Believer muſt needs know that he hath no otherwiſe any Title to Pardon, than as he is purified by the Blood of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Heb. 9.</note> 
               <hi>without the ſhedding of which there would have been no Remiſsion:</hi> hence he dares not, nay he cannot goe on to live in Sinne, becauſe by ſo doing, he ſhall adde New Wounds, New Sorrowes, New Marks of Diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to <hi>Chriſt, by whoſe Stripes alone</hi> he muſt expect <hi>to be healed.</hi> Adde to this, that the <hi>Spirit of God,</hi> which, by quickning the <hi>Immortall Seed of the Word,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 51.</note> begets Faith, is a <hi>clean Spirit,</hi> and will not ſuffer Sinne to cohabit with it ſelf, but Mortifies, Subdues and Quels it, according to that of the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.9.</note> 
               <hi>Ye are not in the Fleſh, but in the Spirit,</hi> i. e. Ye walk not after the Fleſh, but after the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, <hi>if ſo be the Spirit of Chriſt dwelleth in you:</hi> and again, <hi>If Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">verſ. 10.</note> i. e. his Spirit, <hi>be in you, the Body is dead, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Sinne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">verſ. 13.</note> i. e. it dies to ſinne: And, <hi>if by the Spirit ye mortifie the deeds of the Fleſh, ye ſhall live:</hi> All which pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces imply, that it is the Spirits proper buſineſs to <hi>Morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie Sinne,</hi> there is no True Life without it. So that put all this together; Since 1. Gods pardoning Sinne for the ſake of Chriſt, is the higheſt expreſſion of Love imagin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able;<note place="margin">1. Joh. 4.10.</note> as the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> cries out, <hi>Herein is Love!</hi> i. e. <hi>Love</hi> to an Hyperbole, Love beyond any degree of compariſon; <hi>not that we loved God, but that he loved us, and ſent his Sonne to be the Propitiation of our Sinnes.</hi> 2. Since this expreſſion of Love on Gods part, cannot
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:55864:19"/> be embraced by Faith on ours, but it muſt needs beget Love again; as the Sun beams cannot fix themſelves di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly upon the Earth, but they will conveigh Warmth and Heat together with themſelves. 3. Since whereever Love is engendred, it is always Active, carrying out the Soul with unquiet longings after Union with, and till that can be compaſſed, of Likeneſs to the Object it loves. As the Earth no ſooner conceives Heat, by the Action of the Sunne, but preſently returns and reflects it back again. Laſtly, Since the Spirit of God, which dwells in a Believer, is alwayes actuating and blowing up this Love, and improving the ſtrength of it, eſpecially in the ſubduing of Sinne, upon this conſideration, becauſe Sinne is contrary to the Nature of God, and to the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Chriſt; from hence it demonſtrably follows,—that the beſt way to Mortifie Sinne, is rightly to conceive of the Freeneſs of Gods Grace in pardoning it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
               </label> This may ſerve to ſhow us the True Nature of <hi>Justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying Faith:</hi> To think, as perhaps ſome careleſs men doe, that Faith is nothing elſe but a Confident Perſwaſion, that our Sinnes are pardoned for the ſake of Chriſt, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any other notable Effect upon us; this is, at the beſt, an Ungrounded Fancy, which will in the end deceive us. From what I have ſaid, it may appear, that True Juſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying Faith carries along with it theſe two Inſeperable Effects;</p>
            <p n="1">1. It pacifies the Conſcience, it begets a Calm within. When a Sinner firſt begins to be troubled for Sinne, there muſt needs be a kind of Earthquake and Tempeſt in the Soul; as God ſaith of the wicked, that he hath <hi>no Peace,</hi> but <hi>he is like a troubled Sea, which cannot reſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa 57.19.</note> A wicked man is not more Eager and Impatient to commit Sinne, than he is troubled and diſquieted after it, for whenever
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:55864:20"/> he cools and can be at leaſure to conſider what he hath done, he can propoſe nothing to himſelf but matter of Anguiſh and Vexation; without, there is the Law com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining, and God ſentencing; within, Conſcience accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and Sinne condemning. In this Tumult and Hurry of Thoughts, if there be but dropped into any, ſo much ſtrength of Faith, as to lay faſt hold upon Gods generall Pardon (like <hi>Eaſther</hi> catching at the <hi>Golden Scepter,</hi> when it was ſtretched out to her) preſently the ſtorm is laid, and a marvellous calm enſues. As the Apoſtle hath it,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.1.</note> 
               <hi>Being juſtified by Faith, we have Peace with God, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> I doe not ſpeak this, as if I thought that Faith did exclude all manner of <hi>Doubting;</hi> but that it doth expell Diſtraction. For to doubt is ſo much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with Faith, that I take it for granted, there never was, nor ordinarily can be, any True Faith without it. As at the Creation, Night did precede Day, ſo in Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, Darkneſs and Ignorance did precede the Enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of Faith; and Doubting, like a Miſt, doth ſtill at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend it, becauſe our Faith, like our Knowledge, in this life neither is nor can be perfect, for then it would no longer be Faith but Fruition. Yet this Doubting, which, like an Allay, God ſuffers to be mixed (with the ſtrong Wine of Faith,) need not at all diſturb our Peace of Conſcience, but rather is left, as the <hi>Canaanites</hi> were, to teach <hi>Iſrael</hi> to warre,<note place="margin">Jude 2.</note> to quicken our endeavour, and to make us diligent in the uſe of thoſe means, whereby we may be yet more confirmed and ſetled.</p>
            <p n="2">2. True Faith, as it Pacifies the Conſcience, ſo it Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifies the Heart;<note place="margin">Acts 15.9.</note> as the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks, that <hi>God</hi> did <hi>put no difference</hi> between the Jews and Gentiles, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he <hi>purified their Hearts by Faith.</hi> Which is ſo inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable an Effect of True Faith, that though <hi>Juſtification</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:55864:20"/> be not <hi>Sanctification,</hi> yet it is never without it; and therefore they are ſometimes put one for the other, as <hi>he that is juſt,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>let him be juſtified ſtill.</hi> i. e. let him goe on to be more Holy.<note place="margin">Rev. 22.11.</note> And to the <hi>Corinthians— Ye are waſhed, ye are Sanctified,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.11.</note> 
               <hi>ye are Juſtified in the name of the Lord Jeſus, and by the Spirit of our God.</hi> So—<hi>By his mercy he ſaved us,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 3 5, 7.</note> 
               <hi>by the waſhing of Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, and renewing of the Holy Ghoſt; That being juſtified by his Grace, we ſhould be made Heirs.</hi> Where Holineſs, which is an Effect and Fruit of Juſtification, is made to precede it; onely to ſhow the Fixed and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-failing union betwixt them. Now <hi>Faith</hi> produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth Holineſs, not onely becauſe it is begot by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, which is a Spirit of Purity; but becauſe it entitles us to all the Promiſes, which are alwayes urged as Motives unto Purity. <hi>Ye are clean,</hi> ſaith our Saviour to his Diſciples, <hi>through the Word</hi> i. e. of Comfort,<note place="margin">Joh 15.3.</note> 
               <hi>which I have ſpoken to you:</hi> and the Apoſtle having alleaged the Promiſe of God, wherein he ſaid,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 7 1.</note> 
               <hi>he would walk and dwell in his People;</hi> from thence he inferres, <hi>having therefore theſe Promiſes, let us cleanſe our ſelves from all Filthineſs both of Fleſh and Spirit.</hi> So <hi>Peter, God hath given to us many Rich and Precious Promiſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.4.</note> 
               <hi>that thereby we might be partakers of a divine Nature,</hi> having eſcaped, or <hi>fled from that corruption which is in the world through Lust.</hi> And <hi>John</hi> telling us that hereafter we ſhould be like to Chriſt, becauſe <hi>we ſhould ſee him as he is, i. e.</hi> in his utmoſt radiance and luſtre of Glory,—<hi>He then,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that hath this Hope,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Joh. 3.3.</note> 
               <hi>purifies himſelf as he is Pure.</hi> A right Believer enters into Heaven with Chriſt, and labours to live as a Citizen, not of that world he is in, but of that to which he belongs; and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares himſelf for the Reception of Glory, by cleanſing
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:55864:21"/> his Soul with the Infuſions of Grace.<note place="margin">Jac. 2.</note> Let every one then, who would paſs for a Believer, follow the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>James</hi> Advice, and try his <hi>Faith by his Works;</hi> for as Water ſavours of the Veſſell, ſo all our Actions have a Tincture and Reliſh from Faith; if that once be True and Sincere, it influences all we doe; and he that indeed believes in Chriſt, lives onely in and to him. But if our Faith be Falſe and Counterfeit, then we have crooked Ends, we preſently vary our Walking according to the worlds Compaſs, and lye at catch for ſuch Gales to drive us,<note place="margin">Rev. 3.1.</note> as are blown upon us by Popular Applauſe. In ſhort, like the Church of <hi>Sardis, we have a name to live, but indeed are dead.</hi> So that where we ſee one Unholy in his Life, we need not to diſpute, but he is an Unbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in his Heart, and all the while he is ſo, he ought to conclude himſelf Unjuſtified. And ſo much for the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Point.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>3</label> The third and laſt Point, in the generall Obſervation was this; That <hi>a Believer muſt not think he hath arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved unto the Truth of his Profeſsion, untill he is Dead to Sinne.</hi> What it is <hi>to be Dead to Sinne,</hi> the Apoſtle explains afterwards,<note place="margin">verſ. 6.</note> when he calls it <hi>a crucifying of the old man together with Chriſt, that the Body of Sinne may be aboliſhed;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col 3.6.</note> and in another place, <hi>a Mortifying of our Earthly members:</hi> the importance of which Phraſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounts to this; that a Believer muſt keep no truce with, nor give any Quarter to Sinne; he muſt not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly not hearken to its Motions, but ſtrangle them in the Birth; and labour to bring himſelf unto that Temper, that he may have as little appetite to Sinne, as a Dead man to doe any Action of Life. And the Reaſons are,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> Firſt, Becauſe there is to be a conformity between
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:55864:21"/> Chriſt, and a true Chriſtian; As all the parts of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours life, are written for our Example, ſo his Death too ought to be Ours, in Reſemblance and Imitation; we muſt, in the Apoſtle <hi>Pauls</hi> language,<note place="margin">Rom. 6.5.</note> 
               <hi>be planted to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether into the likeneſs of his Death;</hi> and that is by <hi>cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifying our Old man,</hi> i. e. by gibbeting thoſe Luſts, which are the ſhame and Ignominy of our Nature;<note place="margin">Phil. 3.10.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> therefore tells us, that he laboured for nothing more, than to attain <hi>unto a Fellowſhip in Chriſts ſufferings, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made conformable to his Death:</hi> which conſiſts not onely in ſuffering for him, but in dying with him, in that Part, which is onely our Clogge and Hindrance; and, as a Mudwall keeps off the light of the Sunne, ſo doth this <hi>Fleſh</hi> onely ſtoppe the Entrance, and hinder the actings of a Spirituall Life: Therefore the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">Rom. 6.10.</note> drawing a Parallel between Chriſt and a Believer, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forceth it thus; <hi>As Chriſt died and roſe again, ſo reckon ye your ſelves to be dead indeed to Sinne, but alive unto God in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord.</hi> So that the Death of Sinne, is the Life of the Soul; and therein a fit reſemblance of a Riſen Saviour.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> Secondly, The Promiſe of a Crown, is onely made to Conquerours: <hi>To him that overcometh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 3.21.</note> 
               <hi>will I give to ſit with me on my Throne:</hi> Now to Conquer, is not to fight or skirmiſh a little, but to renew the combate, and purſue it, till we have got the Enemy within our Power: So our Duell with Sinne, ſhould be <hi>ad Internecionem,</hi> to the utter ruine and extirpation of it: Since the Price is our Souls, which we have no way to ſave, but by killing this Adverſary.<note place="margin">Heb. 13.4.</note> The Apoſtle therefore exhorting the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> to endure Afflictions, uſeth this as a Motive, <hi>Ye have not as yet reſiſted unto blood, fighting againſt Sinne.</hi> As if he had ſaid, Ye have as yet done juſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:55864:22"/> for this Warfare againſt Sonne, is never to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, but with the Death and Deſtruction of one of the Combatants.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>3</label> Laſtly, When we have done all, <hi>Sinne</hi> will ſtill be in us.<note place="margin">Rom. 7.20.</note> So the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> found, when he complains, that <hi>it is no longer I which doe theſe things, but Sinne which dwelleth in me:</hi> And then preſently cries out in great paſſion, like a man half diſtracted, <hi>who ſhall deliver me from this Body of Sinne and of Death?</hi>
               <note place="margin">verſ. 24.</note> meaning thereby thoſe Reliques of Originall Corruption, which like a Fatall Poiſon; will not in this life be ſo totally emptied out of the Soul, but ſtill ſome drops will remain behind, to embitter our Lives, and to exerciſe our Graces, The moſt we can doe, will be to diſarm this Enemy, for we cannot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> him; to pull him from the Throne, ſince we cannot caſt him out of the Houſe. For it alwayes lies within, like Leaven, ſpreading its infection; or like Fire; if not watched, enflaming our whole man, being it ſelf firſt <hi>inflamed of Hell.</hi> Sinne may lye quiet in the Soil, like ſparks raked up in Aſhes, which, upon the Addition of new Fuell, onely rageth the more <hi>There is</hi> ſaith <hi>Job, Hope of a Tree,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job. 14.7.</note> 
               <hi>when it is cut down, yet if the Root abide in the Earth, by the Sent of Water it may flouriſh and ſpring afreſhe,</hi> ſo there is fear of Sinne, becauſe the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ter</hi> abides in us, and is alwayes reſtleſs and importunate in its Actings. As a Cloud, however Thin and Empty at firſt, yet if there be a rough Wind to ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it, it ſoon over ſpreads the whole Face of Heaven; ſo Sinne in the Soul, hath alwayes a Furious and Eager Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to blow it up, which ſhould make us carefull to throw out the evil <hi>Firment</hi> leaſt it ſhould ſowr the whole Maſs, and by its corrupt quality, infect whatever it mixeth with.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:55864:22"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
               </label> This may ſerve to rectifie their miſtakes, who think it a very facile and eaſie matter to be a Chriſtian. Were there indeed no more required, then to keep <hi>modum pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candi,</hi> to regulate our <hi>vile Actions,</hi> and to preſerve a mean in ſinning, this would not at all be hard; ſuch a meaſure is atteinable by meer Morality: The Heathen, whoſe Lives we read of, had many of them this degree in great Perfection; whoſe beſt virtues were onely <hi>vitia temperata, well mingled and Allayed Vices.</hi> Their light, how glorious and great ſoever it ſeems, was nothing elſe but Coloured Darkneſs; and their beſt Heats, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rebuted cold; ſufficient to ſatisfie the world, and to get Applauſe with Men; but as for Inward Purity, and Heart-Mortification, that was a thing they never dreamt of; this was a task reſerved for our Saviours followers. He hath not minced the matter, when he tells us, that <hi>the way to Heaven</hi> is <hi>a Streight and</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, i. e. <hi>a ſqueezed, preſſed</hi> and <hi>Narrowed way;</hi> ſo pent up,<note place="margin">Mat. 7.</note> and very ſtreight, that no Wind of Ambition, no Tumour of Pride, no running-Sore of Luſt will enter there; he tells us plainly, that we may take our choice, either <hi>cut off our Hands,</hi> i. e. abridg our ſelves of our moſt Uſefull and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable Sinnes, or elſe <hi>into Hell fire;</hi> it will certainly be very dreadfull to endure the one, and it muſt needs be painfull to doe the other. Hence <hi>Fear</hi> and <hi>Trembling. Watchfullneſs</hi> and <hi>Sollicitude</hi> are ſo often called for; we muſt be alwayes upon our Guard, becauſe ever in a fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing poſture, which is a very uneaſie ſervice. And theſe being the Termes, upon which we are to follow Chriſt; it is very ſad to conſider, what a Liberty, both in Life and Language, even Profeſſors of Religion doe take, as if they had a mind to try, how neer they could come to Sinne, without actuall Sinning. We uſe to be afraid of the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:55864:23"/> ſhadow of a Lion; and in a bodily diſtemper, none wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly would venture upon a little Poiſon, leaſt by acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent it ſhould prove Mortall. Why we ſhould not be as carefull to avoid thoſe Sinnes, which none but fools count Little, is a Queſtion we cannot aſſoil, if we either value our Souls, or prize our Peace with God, with whom to break in little things, is great Preſumption. It will be to no purpoſe to ſcape greater Corruption, if leſs may be ſufficient to damn us.<note place="margin">Rom. 6.14.</note> One Chain ties the Slave as faſt to his Oar, as if he had a thouſand; ſo doth one Luſt bind up the Sinner unto Satans ſervice; ſince all the while it reigns, it proclaims that Sinne is our Maſter.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> To exhort all <hi>Believers</hi> to ſet upon this Duty; as for others, they have no skill in it; it is a peculiar Task for ſuch, as have the <hi>Life of Faith;</hi> and this they ought ſo much the more earneſtly be excited to, in that, all the while they allow themſelves in any one Sinne, they are <hi>Eſtranged from the Life of God;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Joh. 1.7.</note> if we expect to have fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with him, <hi>we muſt walk in the Light, as he is in the Light:</hi> As Darkneſs, is nothing elſe but the Abſence of the Sunnes Light; ſo Sinne, which the Apoſtle calls <hi>Spirituall Darkneſs,</hi> is nothing elſe but the Abſence of the <hi>Light of Gods Countenance,</hi> which while it ſhines up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſoul, it preſerves it not only from Diſcomfort, but likewiſe from Dangerous ſtumblings. It is indeed very poſſible, for a True Believer, through heedleſneſs and inadvertency, to fall into ſome Groſs Sinnes, as <hi>David, Hezekiah</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> did, but yet as while they lye in them, their condition ſeems little to differ from that of <hi>Reprobates;</hi> ſo when they begin to recover out of them, we may learn from the Practice of thoſe foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Saints, that their Peace with God, and Aſſurance of his Favour is not recovered without great Expence of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:55864:23"/> Tears and Sorrow. Every Sinne therefore is to be <hi>mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified,</hi> if for no other reſpect, yet for this, in that any one allowed and countenanced in the Soul, will caſt a cloud upon all our Graces, and hinder us for the time from diſcerning the Truth and Sincerity of any. As we therefore prize our own Peace, and Senſe of Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with God, ſo muſt we beſtirre our ſelves, to keep every Corruption from breaking out and prevailing. For the effecting of which, the obſerving of theſe Rules will be very neceſſary.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Diſtinguiſh carefully between the <hi>Naturall</hi> and the <hi>Sinfull</hi> Deſires of the Soul. There are ſome Deſires, <hi>viz.</hi> of <hi>Food,</hi> of <hi>Reſt,</hi> of <hi>Raiment,</hi> &amp;c. which as they are <hi>Naturall,</hi> ſo they are <hi>Innocent</hi> too; Our Saviour him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf was not without them, the Apoſtle ſaith,<note place="margin">Heb. 4.15.</note> 
               <hi>He was tempted in all things as we are,</hi> i. e. with <hi>Hunger,</hi> with <hi>Cold</hi> and <hi>Nakedneſs, yet without Sinne.</hi> The Body, as it is a creature of God, is good and muſt be provided for; and therefore the <hi>Mortification of the Body,</hi> conſiſts not, in denying it the Neceſſaries of Life, but in Abridging it of its Irregular and Senſuall Appetites.<note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.8.</note> 
               <hi>Having Food and Raiment,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>let us be therewith content:</hi> from whence it follows, that either through <hi>Want,</hi> to be Deſtitute; or through <hi>Will,</hi> to deprive our ſelves of <hi>Food</hi> and <hi>Raiment,</hi> is our <hi>Miſery,</hi> and not our <hi>Mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. They that are in the Fleſh cannot pleaſe God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.8.</note> The meaning is not, they that are in the <hi>Body,</hi> cannot pleaſe God; for ſo it is our duty to pleaſe him; but, they that walk in the Vanity and Senſuality of their Fleſhly Mind, cannot pleaſe God: Such as commit thoſe Actions that the Apoſtle hath branded with the Name of <hi>Works of the Fleſh;</hi> as, <hi>Adultery, Fornication, Uncleanneſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5.22.</note> 
               <hi>Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:55864:24"/> &amp;c. theſe cannot pleaſe God, becauſe they walk in Wayes directly contrary to the Holineſs and Spirituality of his Commands. But where the Appetite is hedged in and bounded within thoſe limits, that God hath appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, there <hi>to come Eating and Drinking,</hi> as our Saviour did, may more redound <hi>to the Glory of God,</hi> in our thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Uſing of his Bounty, than any Forced and uncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded Abſtinence. So that all thoſe Wayes of <hi>Morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication,</hi> which are now preſcribed in the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> and too much doted on by men that love to be talked on for their <hi>Sanctity,</hi> are but the Old, Needleſs and Sinfull Methods of the Phariſees, revived with greater Rigour and Auſterity; which conſiſt, as the Apoſtle hath it, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Col. 2.23.</note> in <hi>Unmercifullneſs to, and not ſparing of, the Body;</hi> and ſeem to have a Face of Wiſdome and True Holineſs, but indeed are meer Folly; as nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reaching to (pull out the Core of Sinne, which lies within; nor being able to keep the practiſers of them from Exchanging a Carnall Luſt for Spirituall Pride: and ſo inſtead of right ſubduing the Body, they onely ſwell and puff up the Soul.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Pray for the Spirit of Chriſt; without which we ſhall be too Weak to ſet upon and conquer this In-bred Enemy. <hi>Whatever is born of the Fleſh, is Fleſh,</hi> i. e. both Prall and Sinfull: and <hi>Fleſh</hi> will never be able to ſubdue <hi>Fleſh;</hi> the Spirit, which alwayes acts in Believers, muſt be ſet awork about it.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.13.</note> 
               <hi>If by the Spirit, ye mortifie the deeds of the Fleſh,</hi> faith the Apoſtle, <hi>ye ſhall live,</hi> i. e. ye ſhall live indeed, for <hi>it is this Spirit alone that quickens.</hi> And whoever thinks of mortifying his Corruptions, without this ſupernaturall Aſſiſtance, begins a Combate wherein he is ſure to be foiled; ſince not onely his own
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:55864:24"/> Nature, but likewiſe the <hi>Powers of Hell</hi> are violently bent againſt him; and how ſhall he ſcape the <hi>Malice</hi> and <hi>Wickedneſs</hi> of thoſe <hi>Evill ſpirits;</hi> unleſs the <hi>Spirit of God,</hi> which will alwayes reſide where his preſence is ſollicited, doth ſecure the ſoul and give us ſtrength for the Victory.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Labour for the Aſſurance of the Pardon of your Paſt Sinnes: As he that runnes a Race, muſt firſt put off his Fetters; ſo whoever engages againſt the Violence of his Luſts, muſt firſt be ſatisfied, that his paſt offences are forgiven; or elſe the ſenſe of Sinne unpardoned will lye, like a Weight upon him, and inſtead of exciting him to ſtrive againſt it, betray him to its Aſſaults.</p>
            <p>For the Attaining of this, beſides what the Spirit of God may immediately work, (which caſe falls not under any Rule, ſince the <hi>Spirit blowes where and when it pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth</hi>) there is no Method can be given better, than that which I have hitherto been inſiſting on, and that is to caſt our ſelves upon Gods Free-Grace in Chriſt; which who ſo doth, is as certain never to miſcarry, as the Word of God, and the Experience of all the Saints now Triumph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Heaven, can make him.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
